All right, Chapter 4, Hemostasis and Related Disorders.
This is our first section. It's an introduction.
It lays the framework for the rest of the chapter.
The idea here is that we need to recall that we've got blood vessels.
Obviously, the role of those blood vessels is to carry blood through the body.
Remember that the blood vessels line by endothelial cells,
and the endothelial cells sit on top of basement membrane.
Again, endothelial cells sitting on top of basement membrane.
Now, the integrity of these blood vessels is essential.
Without the integrity of these blood vessels, blood would not be able to reach the tissues.
We don't want blood leaking out here.
We want blood going through the vessel and to reach the organs.
If there happens to be damage to this tube, then the damage needs to be repaired,
and the way by which we repair the damage is called hemostasis.
Now, hemostasis works by forming a little area of a band-aid.
For example, let's say that there's disruption here.
This band-aid would form, and this band-aid is called a thrombus or a clot.
So wherever there's vessel injury, a clot or a thrombus will form.
Now, in order to form that clot, we actually have two distinct stages.
The first stage is called primary hemostasis, and the second stage is called secondary hemostasis.
In primary hemostasis, the goal is to form something called the platelet plug.
And the platelet plug is just an adhesion and an aggregation of platelets in the region of the injury.
Now, that platelet plug is weak, and so in order to stabilize that platelet plug,
we have something called secondary hemostasis.
Secondary hemostasis then comes in and stabilizes the platelet plug.
And so this is a little bit of the normal.
Now, let's just read together what we have written in the text.
So I tell you that the integrity of the blood vessels is necessary to carry blood to the tissues,
that the damage to the wall of the vessel would be repaired by hemostasis,
and that hemostasis involves a formation of a thrombus or a clot at the site of injury.
Hemostasis, of course, occurs in two stages, primary and secondary.
In primary hemostasis, we form a weak platelet plug,
and the key thing here is that that platelet plug is weak.
Now, of course, the platelet plug is formed by an interaction between the platelets and the vessel wall.
Then what comes in is secondary hemostasis comes in,
and secondary hemostasis, the goal is to stabilize that platelet plug.
So again, secondary hemostasis stabilizes the platelet plug,
and that's all mediated by that complex thing called the coagulation cascade.
So with this little bit of introduction, we can now move forward into the disorders.
The first type of disorder that we want to talk about are those that are related to primary hemostasis.
Now, of course, to understand these primary hemostasis disorders,
you really have to understand normal primary hemostasis, and so let's go there next.
Now, when there is disruption of the blood vessel,
okay, so we've got a blood vessel, and again, lined by endothelial cells,
and of course, the blood vessel endothelial cells sit on top of a basement membrane.
When there is disruption, as I've drawn here,
the very first thing is a little bit of a knee-jerk reaction.
So step one of this primary hemostasis will be that there will be transient vasoconstriction of the damaged vessels.
Now, this is very important to note because actually examiners like to go after it.
Step one, the blood vessel will actually rapidly constrict.
I think of it as a knee-jerk reaction.
When you get a little bit of an injury, you kind of pull away from something.
I don't know, if you touch something hot, you'll pull your hand away.
When the blood vessel gets damaged, it just clamps down very quickly.
And that perhaps is to decrease the amount of blood supply going to the region for a moment
before hemostasis can kick in,
or it might also be that the blood vessel is sort of just shaking itself to awaken.
Now, you need to know for the purposes of examinations that this step one is actually mediated by two things.
The first is neural stimulation, so it's a neural reflex for the blood vessel to clamp down when there's initial injury.
And number two, and perhaps a little more high yield,
is that the endothelial cells themselves have a molecule called endothelion.
So that when this endothelial cell, for example, gets disrupted,
endothelion will be released,
and that will cause a very quick transient vasoconstriction of the damaged vessel.
Now, the next step is that von Willebrand's factor will come in
and will line the surface of the area of the disruption
at the level of the subendothelial collagen.
Now, you realize that when the endothelial cells are disrupted,
we've now exposed both the basement membrane, which contains collagen,
as well as the connective tissue underneath, which contains collagen.
That collagen then allows for von Willebrand's factor to actually bind.
So von Willebrand's factor will bind,
and then von Willebrand's factor will act as a linker molecule
for the platelets to bind to this region.
And the way by which the platelets bind is by using a receptor called GP1B.
So the platelets will use GP1B to bind von Willebrand's factor,
and that is called platelet adhesion, and it is step number two.
Platelet adhesion, the platelets bind von Willebrand's factor via GP1B.
Important to note, for the purposes of examinations,
where does von Willebrand's factor come from?
Von Willebrand's factor comes from two sources.
Number one, the platelet itself has some von Willebrand's factor within it,
but number two, and the most important,
is that the endothelial cells have von Willebrand's factor themselves.
And so the vast majority of the von Willebrand's factor
actually comes from the endothelial cell.
Unfortunately, that's not sufficient.
You do need to know one more thing,
and that is that within the endothelial cell,
it's the Weibull-Pilotti body that actually holds the von Willebrand's factor.
Remember that the Weibull-Pilotti body is something that we learned about
in normal histology.
It is a body that is viewable by electron microscopy,
and it contains many different substances necessary for endothelial function.
The way I remember the two most important things within the Weibull-Pilotti bodies
is to use the letters to remind me of what's actually in them.
So, for example, the P reminds me that
one of the important molecules in the Weibull-Pilotti body is P-selectin.
And remember, P-selectin, its role was important
when we talked about the selectin speed bumps in our inflammation discussion.
So, I'm not going to go into the details here,
but those P-selectins were important there.
And the W helps me to remember that von Willebrand's factor
is also contained within the Weibull-Pilotti bodies.
Now, that was step two.
Once this binding occurs,
then the next thing that happens is that the platelets get activated,
they undergo shape change,
and then they degranulate.
And so that is step three.
So, adhesion of the platelets to von Willebrand's factor
will then cause a shape change within the platelets,
which then allows for the dumping of mediators
that are going to be necessary for moving this process forward.
And there are two important mediators
that are going to arise from the platelets.
One is going to be ADP,
and ADP is essential,
and the second is going to be thromboxane A2.
And remember that thromboxane A2
is a derivative of platelet cyclooxygenase,
and that's high yield.
ADP is present within the dense corp ranules,
and thromboxane A2 is a derivative of platelet cyclooxygenase.
Now, the important things about ADP and thromboxane A2,
ADP induces the platelets to express another receptor,
and the other receptor is going to be something called GP2B3A.
Now, a GP2B3A receptor is essential for platelet aggregation.
Aggregation is when all the platelets join together
at this particular spot.
Remember that adhesion was the platelet binding
to the area of exposed subendothelial collagen via von Willebrand's factor.
Aggregation is when the platelets begin to aggregate
on top of those adhesed platelets.
So ADP is essential for the expression of GP2B3A.
And then TXA2, thromboxane A2,
will be the signal that will allow for further platelet aggregation.
So platelets will begin to aggregate here,
and one important thing to note
is that the important linker molecule that the platelets use
to aggregate to one another is called fibrinogen.
So this important linker molecule here is called fibrinogen,
and that, again, is essential to know as well.
Okay, so with that in mind, let's read a little bit of our text.
So I say that primary hemostasis occurs via four steps.
In the very first step,
we get transient vasoconstriction of the damaged vessel.
This is mediated by reflex neural stimulation and endothelion,
which comes from the endothelial cells.
Step two, you get the platelet adhesion
to the surface of the disrupted vessels.
And again, von Willebrand's factor will bind
that subendothelial collagen.
The platelets will bind that using GP1B.
Where does von Willebrand's factor come from?
From the Weibol-Pilotti bodies and from the platelets,
in particular the alpha granules of the platelets.
Now then, that will cause platelet degranulation.
So the adhesion will cause a shape change,
which then results in degranulation
with release of multiple mediators.
Remember that ADP, which comes from the dense granules,
then promotes the exposure of GP2B3A
on the receptor of the platelets,
and thromboxyne A2, a derivative of cyclooxygenase,
very high yield again,
derivative of platelet cyclooxygenase,
further promotes platelet aggregation.
And platelet aggregation is going to occur via GP2B3A
using fibrinogen as a linker molecule.
Now important to note, and I've already stated,
that this results in a formation of a platelet plug.
That platelet plug is weak.
It doesn't have the ability to withstand
a tremendous amount of force.
And so in order to further stabilize that platelet plug,
we're going to undergo secondary hemostasis,
which basically is the job of the coagulation cascade.
But of course in this particular section,
we're dealing with disorders of primary hemostasis,
so we're not going to focus on the coagulation cascade yet.
That's going to come up a little bit later.
Now what about disorders of primary hemostasis?
How can we think about those?
Well those are basically, for the most part,
not always, but for the most part,
they're going to be due to abnormalities in platelets.
And there's two types of abnormalities
that we can have in platelets.
We can have a quantitative abnormality
where we don't have enough platelets.
The quantity is bad.
Or we can have a qualitative problem
where the quality of the platelets is no good,
but we have enough platelets, for example.
And so these are the two ways we want to think about
disorders of primary hemostasis
when we're in the context of abnormalities of the platelets.
Quantitative disorders and qualitative disorders.
Now when patients have disorders of primary hemostasis,
they're going to present with some very classical signs and symptoms.
And the most important is that
they're going to get mucosal and skin bleeding.
This is the predominant picture of a patient
with a disorder of primary hemostasis.
So what are some examples of mucosal bleeding?
Well, any mucosal site can bleed.
For example, the patient can have nose bleeding or epistaxis.
They can have coughing up a blood or hemopysis,
GI bleeding, hematuria with blood in the urine,
or menorrhagia, heavy menstrual bleeding
because the endometrium is also a mucosal surface.
So these are some classic signs and symptoms,
and actually the most common is epistaxis.
And that's why I sort of went after that one
and highlighted it for you as I was talking.
Now one of the feared complications of having a low platelet count
is intracranial bleeding.
And this occurs when there is severe thrombocytopenia.
So that's something to just bury away in the back of our minds.
That, you know, mucosal bleeding is not so bad.
We can deal with it.
But the feared complication is that
as the platelet count goes down, for example,
if there was a quantitative problem with platelets,
then intracranial bleeding would,
the risk of intracranial bleeding would increase
and we'd become more and more worried about that particular complication.
Now we can also get skin bleeding with disorders of primary hemostasis.
For example, patients can develop petechiae or pinpoint bleeding in the skin.
They can develop purpura, which are slightly larger,
measuring approximately 3 millimeters or greater.
And finally, they can develop ecchymosis,
which measure approximately greater than 1 centimeter.
And so these are varying sizes of bleeding within the skin.
Now I'd like to alert you to the point that there is an error in your text here
and that the size of purpura and ecchymosis has been reversed.
So again, purpura are greater than 3 millimeters
and ecchymosis are areas of bleed greater than 1 centimeter in the skin.
Now another symptom of skin bleeding might be easy bruising.
So that would have been patients with thrombocytopenia
or patients, why don't I say, with disorders of primary hemostasis
would also exhibit easy bruising.
Now one of the important things to note,
that when we talk about petechiae, ecchymosis, and purpura,
when we get this type of bleeding,
we're really talking, it really is a sign of thrombocytopenia.
Now what I mean by that is,
remember when we talked about the disorders that could arise,
we said there can be a quantitative disorder of platelets
or a qualitative disorder of platelets.
Well patients who have qualitative disorders of platelets,
they normally don't get petechiae.
However, patients who have quantitative,
where the number is down, they get petechiae.
And so that's a little,
that's just a little side note to be aware of.
Here's what the petechiae look like.
They're these little tiny bleeds
that are exhibited on the skin here.
And so this is the classic image of petechiae.
You can see here that perhaps we're getting
into the possibility of having a little bit of ecchymosis here
where the bleeds may be slightly larger as well.
When a patient, sorry, not a platelet,
when a patient has a disorder of primary hemostasis,
you've got mucosal bleeding, you've got skin bleeding,
then you're going to want to look at some laboratory studies
in order to try to determine where the problem is.
So, for example, the platelet count can be very helpful.
It tells us how many platelets there are.
If we had a qualitative, i.e., problem with the number of platelets,
of course, the platelet count would reveal that.
The normal platelet count is anywhere from 150,000 to 400,000,
150,000 to 400,000 per microliter.
Less than that, we would begin to potentially see problems,
especially when the platelet count is less than 50K or 50,000.
The bleeding time is also a useful laboratory study.
The bleeding time, basically, the idea here is that you prick the patient
and you see how long it takes them before they stop bleeding.
The normal is anywhere from 2 to 7 minutes.
So, normally, in about 2 up to 7 minutes, the patient should stop bleeding.
However, when there's quantitative problems or qualitative problems,
the bleeding will be prolonged.
And so, that's the bleeding time.
Now, the reason why I argue whether that's useful is perhaps most places in the country
wouldn't be doing this anymore.
It's a little bit of a primitive test, but it does show up on examinations,
and so I kept it in your text.
The next way by which we could assess the patient's platelets is to look at them,
and we can do that by blood smear.
You take the patient's blood, you smear it on a slide,
and you get a peek at what the platelets look like.
It helps you to tell how many platelets are present.
We can assess the number of platelets, at least in rough estimate.
We can assess the number of platelets by looking at them on the slide,
and we can also assess the size of the platelets,
and you'll see that there will be some disorders where the size of the platelets will matter,
and so that is how the blood smear would be helpful.
And then, finally, we can do a bone marrow biopsy to assess the platelets,
and the way this works is that remember that the megakaryocytes are the cells
that are actually producing the platelets.
So we can ask the question, if, for example, platelet count is low,
are there megakaryocytes?
Maybe it's that we don't have megakaryocytes in the bone marrow,
and that's why the platelet count is low.
So the bone marrow biopsy is also very helpful.
The first of the disorders that we want to discuss is called ITP.
This is an autoimmune production of IgG against platelet antigens.
For example, one of the antigens on platelets is GP2B3A.
Remember, GP2B3A is the receptor that's used for cross-linking of the platelets via fibrinogen.
Remember that story we talked about a little bit earlier.
Now, the point here, however, is that the patients get IgG against platelet antigens.
This is the most common cause of thrombocytopenia,
thrombocytopenia low platelets in the blood.
This is the most common cause of thrombocytopenia in both children and adults,
so it's very important to be aware of it.
Now, the antibodies in this particular case, those IgG antibodies that are causing the disease,
are actually produced by the plasma cells in the spleen.
And interestingly, what happens is these antibodies are produced,
they go out into the blood, they bind the platelets,
and when they bind the platelets, the macrophages within the spleen
actually eat those antibody-bound platelets.
So, the antibodies are made in the spleen,
and the platelets that are bound by the antibodies are actually consumed by the macrophages in the spleen.
So, the spleen is making the antibody as well as consuming the platelets that are bound to the antibody.
And, of course, when the platelets are consumed, that's what results in the thrombocytopenia.
Now, the acute form is that form that arises in children.
So, otherwise stated, why don't we take a step back?
This disorder can be divided into something called the acute form and the chronic form.
In the acute form, which classically arises in children,
you see thrombocytopenia weeks after a viral infection or immunization.
Of course, it's due to autoantibody production of an IgG,
which is binding the platelets and resulting in consumption of the platelets.
And this is a self-limited disorder.
It usually resolves by itself within weeks of presentation.
The only thing we have to do is support the patient if the platelet count goes down to a very low value, for example.
In the chronic form, which normally arises in adults,
this is classically seen in women of childbearing age.
Again, it's an autoimmune type of disorder.
And it can be primary or secondary.
Now, primary, we don't really know the cause.
In secondary, it's associated with another disorder, for example, lupus.
Remember in our discussions of lupus that I told you that in lupus,
one of the interesting things about these patients is that most patients with lupus
will have an antibody against something, against one of the cells in the blood.
For example, patients with lupus can produce antibodies against their red blood cells.
They can produce antibodies against their white cells.
They can also produce antibodies against their platelets.
And so lupus is a very important association with us, with ITP,
especially as a secondary cause of ITP.
Now, again, remember that patients who have the chronic form
are going to have this disease for a long period of time,
and that's why it's called the chronic form.
And so it would not be uncommon for these patients to actually have the disease
and eventually to become pregnant just as part of their normal life.
When they become pregnant, it's important to note that
because this is an IgG-mediated disease, the IgG can actually cross the placenta.
IgG has the ability to cross the placenta,
and that can result in thrombocytopenia in the offspring.
Of course, that would be short-lived
because eventually the antibodies would be consumed over time,
and then there would be no more IgG antibody once the baby was born.
But it is important to note that women who have the chronic form
or the long-standing form of ITP
can actually have short-lived thrombocytopenia in their offspring.
Now, what are we going to see on labs?
Well, obviously, we've got idiopathic or immune thrombocytopenia.
Thrombocyto refers to the platelets, and penia means that they're low.
So the platelet count's going to be low
because the platelets are being consumed.
Often, it's less than 50,000 per microliter.
At the same time, I'd like you to know that the PT and PTT are going to be normal.
We haven't touched the coagulation cascade here.
All of the coagulation factors are going to be normal,
and therefore, the PT and the PTT are also going to be normal.
Finally, because we're destroying platelets outside of the bone marrow,
the bone marrow is actually going to respond by trying to produce more platelets.
And as it tries to produce more platelets,
we're going to see a hyperplasia of the megakureocytes.
We're going to see an increased number of megakureocytes on the bone marrow biopsy.
The initial treatment of this disorder is corticosteroids.
If a child needs corticosteroids, they tend to respond very well.
Important to note that the adults with the chronic form,
they can respond initially, but they often relapse
despite the fact that they've been treated with corticosteroids.
One of the interesting things that we can do
if a patient has a symptomatically low platelet count,
let's say the patient has a very low platelet count,
and they're starting to bleed from multiple sites,
and now you're worried that the feared complication
of intracranial bleeding might occur,
and you want to raise the platelet count.
Well, one way to raise the platelet count would be to give the patient IVIG.
Now, what is IVIG?
IV implies that you give it intravenously,
and IG is the immunoglobulin.
So what you do is you give the patient intravenous immunoglobulin.
Now, why would that help?
Well, if you give the patient a ton of immunoglobulin,
what's going to happen is you're going to have the splenic macrophages
to start eating that immunoglobulin instead of the immunoglobulin
that's bound to the platelets.
So it's like throwing a stick at a dog so that it goes the other way.
You throw these little immunoglobulin sticks at the spleen,
and the spleen will start eating those sticks
instead of eating the platelet-bound immunoglobulin.
Basically, you're going to overrun the spleen with all of this IVIG
so that it sits there and consumes the IVIG
and leaves the platelets alone for a little while.
And, of course, you can imagine that once the IVIG gets consumed,
then the spleen will again start eating the immunoglobulin-bound platelets.
So the effect is short-lived, and that's important to know as well.
This is just used to raise the platelet count
when there's symptomatic bleeding.
Basically, you're trying to defend the patient's platelets
from being eaten for a short period of time.
The final treatment and sort of the very last stage treatment
would be to do splenectomy.
Very high yield to know that when a patient gets splenectomy,
you're actually going to eliminate both the source of the antibody
because, remember, the plasma cells in the spleen
were actually making the antibody,
and you're going to eliminate the site of destruction
because, remember, that the macrophages of the spleen
were the cells that were actually eating the antibody-coated platelets.
So splenectomy kind of kills two birds with one stone.
Very important to know that splenectomy kills two birds with one stone,
but it's only performed in refractory cases.
So that's the first disorder that we need to be familiar with.
The second disorder that we want to talk about
is called microangiopathic hemolytic anemia.
It's kind of a mouthful, but if you understand the words,
it's all downhill from there.
Microangiopathic hemolytic anemia.
Now, what does this mean?
Microangio means small blood vessels.
So we're talking about the small blood vessels,
and, of course, these small blood vessels are lined by endothelium.
And then pathic means we've got a pathology in the small blood vessels.
Microangiopathic, pathology in the small blood vessels.
And that pathology is resulting in a hemolytic anemia.
Now, the idea here is that in this particular set of disorders,
you have something called a platelet microthrombus.
So for some reason, and I'll talk about the reasons in a minute,
you get an abnormal aggregation of platelets
forming a platelet microthrombus.
Now, that platelet microthrombus,
guess who has to pass across it?
The red blood cell.
So as the red blood cell crosses that platelet microthrombus,
which is partially occluding the blood vessel,
you're going to get shearing of the blood vessel.
Oh, sorry.
You're going to get shearing of the red blood cell,
which is called a schistocyte.
But that's going to obviously result in hemolysis
because you've now lyced the red blood cell.
You've destroyed it.
So that's called hemolysis when you destroy the red blood cell.
Obviously, here it's occurring within the blood vessel,
and that's why the patients get a hemolytic anemia.
So a hemolytic anemia due to pathology within the small blood vessel.
Again, microangiopathic hemolytic anemia.
Now, what are the complications going to be?
So why don't we start by asking why am I talking about this disorder
in the context of primary hemostatic problems?
Well, as these microthrombi are formed, we're going to consume platelets.
So you're going to use up platelets when these abnormal microthrombi are formed.
And so that's what I say in your book,
that platelets are consumed in the formation of microthrombi.
And, of course, then the red blood cells will be sheared
as they cross those microthrombi, resulting in the formation of schistocytes.
Here's a very high-yield picture, shows up on examinations all the time.
There are a lot of contexts in which we can see this,
but at this point we're going to focus on two disorders.
You'll hear about them in a second.
But this is the schistocyte.
This is the cell that has been sheared as it went across the microthrombus.
And classically, you can see that it's kind of got two points at either end,
and that's a classic morphologic finding.
It looks like a helmet.
Sometimes they call it a helmet cell.
Anyway, this is an indication that the patient's got some sort of
microangiopathic hemolytic anemia going on.
Now, remember that I didn't give you the reason why these microthrombi are occurring.
And there's two classic disorders in which we're going to see
a microangiopathic hemolytic anemia.
The first is TTP, also called thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura.
And the second is HUS, also known as hemolytic uremic syndrome.
In thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura, the problem that arises, again,
is it's the same story that I've already told.
You've got this blood vessel.
And within this blood vessel, you begin to form platelet microthrombi.
Now, what's important to note is why those platelet microthrombi are forming
is that in TTP, or thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura,
look at the name again.
Thrombotic, you're forming these platelet microthrombi.
Thrombocytopenic, that's using up the platelets,
and that's why you get thrombocytopenia.
Purpura, the patients then get bleeds in the skin,
which are purpura, because they've got low platelets.
And one of the signs of low platelets is skin bleeding,
and one of the types of skin bleeding would be purpura.
All right, so that's where the name comes from.
Now, the idea here, and the reason why the patients get these microthrombi,
is this is due to a decrease in an enzyme called ADAMS-TS13.
So that is the enzyme that's decreased in TTP.
Now, what is ADAMS-TS13?
Well, remember that normally when you produce your von Willebrand's factor,
you produce it as multimers.
And those multimers need to be degraded over time,
and the way by which we degrade them
is to chop them up into smaller monomers.
And the enzyme that's necessary to chop up those multimers
into smaller monomers is called ADAMS-TS13.
Let me just illustrate this for you.
If you've got von Willebrand's factor here,
and it's a multimer,
it's got another molecule of von Willebrand's factor here,
and another molecule of von Willebrand's factor here,
the way by which you're going to eventually degrade this molecule
is to chop these things away one by one,
which allows for eventual degradation.
If you don't have the enzyme necessary to chop these things away,
you can't degrade it,
and so it begins to get a pileup,
and these large multimers can lead to abnormal platelet adhesion.
Remember that von Willebrand's factor is necessary for platelet adhesion,
for the platelets to actually bind to the subendothelial collagen.
So you'll get this abnormal platelet adhesion,
and that will then result in the platelets sort of forming these microthrombi.
So very high yield take-home point,
TTP is due to Adams TS-13 deficiency,
or a decrease in Adams TS-13.
And that's what I've highlighted here in your text,
where I say that TTP is due to decreased Adams TS-13.
I tell you in the text that Adams TS-13
normally cleaves von Willebrand's multimers into monomers
so that it can be degraded.
If you don't have the ability to degrade these,
you get large, uncleaved multimers,
which then leads to abnormal platelet adhesion,
resulting in microthrombi.
Again, you recall that adhesion is the step
in which platelets use GP-1b to bind von Willebrand's factor
to stick to the blood vessel.
Now, we can then ask the question,
why, what's causing this decrease in Adams TS-13?
And the answer is that you can get a genetic defect
in which you have a decrease in Adams TS-13,
but the more common reason that you would have a decrease in Adams TS-13
is because you produce an autoantibody against Adams TS-13,
which then results in destruction of Adams TS-13.
And so the classic patient that develops TTP
is an adult female who, as an autoimmune process,
develops an autoantibody,
and that autoantibody then destroys Adams TS-13.
So the classic patient is an adult female.
Now, a second way by which we can get
a microangiopathic hemolytic anemia
is a disorder called HUS.
HUS refers to hemolytic uremic syndrome.
Now, the hemolytic here implies that you've got platelet microthrombi
that results in hemolysis
with shearing of the red blood cells
and the production of schistocytes.
The uremic syndrome implies that this is going to occur
predominantly within the kidney,
causing kidney damage, which will then result in uremia.
And I'm going to talk about the clinical findings
of both of these disorders,
both TTP and HUS, in a moment.
Now, in this particular case,
what's happening is you've got a blood vessel.
Of course, the blood vessel is lined by endothelium,
which sits on top of a basement membrane.
And here you're forming these platelet microthrombi.
Again, I emphasize platelet microthrombi,
just platelets are present here.
And when you get these platelet microthrombi,
you can ask the question, why?
Well, in HUS, the reason why the patients
get the platelet microthrombi
is that they get an infection
with a very special bug
that you have to be familiar with.
It's a very high-yield bug,
and it's called E. coli 015787.
So patients get this E. coli 015787,
and that then results in a varotoxin
being produced by the bug.
It's called E. coli varotoxin,
which damages the endothelial cells.
And when it damages the endothelial cells,
you get platelet microthrombi,
particularly in the kidneys, but also in the brain.
They get platelet microthrombi,
and those platelet microthrombi
will then result in a hemolysis
because the red blood cells will get sheared,
producing schistocytes,
a thrombocytopenia
because the platelets are getting used up.
All right?
And so this is a classic mechanism
by which patients get HUS.
Again, HUS, the key mechanism is E. coli 015787,
super high yield.
Now the next discussion is
who gets E. coli 015787.
Well, that's classically seen in children.
Who get exposure to undercooked beef.
That's the way by which this bug can arise.
That results in a dysentery
in which they get mucousy diarrhea.
And again, that's due to E. coli 015787.
Again, I told you that the bug produces a varotoxin
which damages the endothelial cells
resulting in platelet microthrombi.
Interestingly, the most recent understanding
of this particular disorder
is that that varotoxin
by damaging the endothelial cells
also decreases the amount of ADAMS-TS13.
So the mechanism here is kind of similar to TTP,
which we just talked about.
I guess in TTP,
you get autoimmune destruction
of the ADAMS-TS13.
And in this particular disorder,
it's the E. coli 015787
that damages the endothelial cells,
which also actually leads to a problem
or a decrease in ADAMS-TS13.
But that's sort of the latest information
concerning this disorder.
Now, the clinical findings are very similar
in TTP and HUS.
So if it's thrombotic, thrombocytopenic, purpura,
or hemolytic uremic syndrome,
these are both microangiopathic hemolytic anemias,
as I've already explained,
and the clinical findings are very similar.
So they get skin and mucosal bleeding.
Why would they get skin and mucosal bleeding?
Well, in both cases,
you're getting platelet microthrombi
within the blood vessels, correct?
The problem was that you've got these blood vessels
and you get these platelet microthrombi in them.
The platelet microthrombi result
in the consumption of platelets.
To form this microthrombus,
you're going to use up platelets.
And as you use up platelets,
you're going to have skin and mucosal bleeding
because you're getting thrombocytopenic.
At the same time,
the blood cells have to cross those platelet microthrombi.
They're going to get sheared,
and that's going to give you a microangiopathic,
i.e. in the small blood vessels,
hemolytic anemia.
Hemolysis means the breaking up
or the destruction of red blood cells.
The patients also tend to have fever,
and they get this whole process,
this whole process of forming
these platelet microthrombi
and shearing the red blood cells
within the tissues
occurs primarily within two tissues.
Number one, it occurs in the kidney.
So in both of these diseases,
TTP and HUS,
you're going to have renal insufficiency,
and it also occurs within the CNS.
And so in both of these disorders,
TTP and HUS,
you can have CNS abnormalities.
What's important to note is that in TTP,
the predominant problem is CNS,
and in HUS,
the predominant problem is renal.
And the way you remember that
is that in HUS,
you know that the letters stand for
hemolytic uremic syndrome,
and remember that uremia
is a sign of a renal problem.
The laboratory findings are very straightforward
if you understand the disorders.
Basically, these patients are going to have
thrombocytopenia,
a decrease in platelets.
Again, they're using them
in the formation of the microthrombi.
There's going to be an increased bleeding time
because they don't have good numbers of platelets,
and so rather than being the normal
two to seven minutes,
the bleeding time might be
10 or 15 minutes, for example.
Now, very important to note,
and super high yield,
is that the PT-PTT are classically normal,
especially for exam purposes.
Classically, not necessarily always,
but classically,
the PT-PTT will be normal.
And the idea here is
you haven't activated the coagulation cascade.
When these microthrombi are forming,
what's happening is
you're forming these platelet microthrombi,
but you're not going to the next step
where you actually activate
the coagulation cascade,
and you get cross-linking.
So, the only thing that's happening
is that the platelets are actually aggregating
at that site.
Well, maybe I should say more correctly,
there's adhesion of platelets at that site.
And so, the PT-PTT will be normal
in this disorder.
And that's, again, very important.
The patients will also have anemia
with schistocytes,
and there'll be increased megakaryocytes
on bone marrow biopsy.
Why?
Because as the platelets are being consumed,
the bone marrow will recognize
that there's less platelets in the blood,
and the megakaryocytes will begin
to produce extra platelets
to try to help out the body.
And those extra platelets
have to be produced by extra megakaryocytes.
And so, you'll get hyperplasia
of the megakaryocytes,
and you'll see that on bone marrow biopsy.
The treatment of these disorders,
in particular TTP,
involves plasmapheresis and corticosteroids.
Now, the idea here is that in TTP,
the disorder is due to an autoantibody.
Plasmapheresis is a mechanism
by which you can remove proteins from the blood,
and so you can remove, for example,
by doing plasmapheresis,
you could remove the autoantibody
against ADAMS-TS13,
which was leading to the problem.
At the same time,
by giving corticosteroids,
what you're doing is decreasing production
of the autoantibody,
so that would also be helpful in TTP.
Now, the next set of disorders
that we want to talk about
are those of quality of the platelets.
Remember, I told you that there are
quantitative disorders
in which the number of platelets is down.
For example, in ITP,
the whole idea was that we were losing
our platelet number due to an IgG antibody.
For example, in TTP and in HUS,
these microangiopathic hemolytic anemias,
we were losing our platelet count
due to use of the platelets
to form the microthrombi.
So those were examples of quantitative problems.
Now we're talking about qualitative problems,
problems in which there is an issue
with the quality of the platelets.
The first is called Bernard-Soulier syndrome,
and this is a genetic GP1B deficiency.
Now, of course, if GP1B is deficient,
platelet adhesion cannot occur.
Let's remind ourselves
that when we have this blood vessel
and there is damage to the blood vessel,
the first thing that's going to happen
is transient vasoconstriction.
After transient vasoconstriction,
we're going to have von Willebrand's factor
bind the subendothelial collagen.
Remember, where does von Willebrand's factor
come from?
Number one, the alpha granule of the platelet,
and number two, and more important,
the libel-pilotti body of the endothelial cell.
Now, of course, that von Willebrand's factor
isn't going to bind that exposed
subendothelial collagen,
so it can act as a linker molecule
for the platelets to adhese.
Remember that?
To adhese via a receptor called GP1B.
Now, if the patients don't have that receptor
because there's a genetic deficiency,
i.e. Bernard-Soulier syndrome,
obviously the patients are going to have
bleeding problems because they can't bind
the von Willebrand's factor
and they can't undergo this important step
of adhesion.
So let's see what we say in the book.
Genetic GP1B deficiency,
platelet adhesion is impaired.
What will the blood smear show?
It will show thrombocytopenia
with enlarged platelets.
Now, the reason why these patients
get mild thrombocytopenia
is because if GP1B is not functioning well,
the platelets tend to not live as long
and so the platelets get destroyed.
So that's why they get mild thrombocytopenia
and they get enlarged platelets
because they're producing platelets
a little bit more immature
than they would normally produce
from the bone marrow.
And so you can think about that
being the reason why the platelets
might be enlarged.
But perhaps a funny way to remember this
and one way in which a student
sort of reminded me once
is that in Bernard-Soulier disease,
you get big suckers, big suckers,
meaning he was referring in that particular case
to the enlarged platelets.
Whatever helps you to remember this,
that's the key thing,
that you need to remember
that there is enlarged platelets
on blood smear.
Now the next of the disorders
is called Glansman's thrombasthenia
and this is a genetic defect in GP2B3A.
And guess what's going to happen here?
Platelet aggregation is going to be impaired.
So what's platelet aggregation?
Well remember that if you've got
a damaged blood vessel,
then obviously von Willebrand's factor
is going to come in here
and bind to the subendothelial collagen.
The platelets will then bind
this von Willebrand's factor
using GP1B.
Now of course,
binding of von Willebrand's factor
by GP1B activates the platelets.
They then undergo degranulation
and shape change
and you know that the platelets
are going to release ADP
and they're also going to release
something called TXA2
which is a derivative
of platelet cyclooxygenase.
Now remember that the role of ADP
was what?
Was to cause the platelet
to flip out this particular receptor
and to express a receptor
called GP2B3A.
And you know that that particular receptor
GP2B3A
that that particular receptor
is necessary for the aggregation
of other platelets.
And remember that the next platelet
would come in.
It would also express GP2B3A
and the linking molecule here
is fibrinogen.
So if you...
And that then allows
for platelet aggregation.
Now imagine if you don't have GP2B3A
this particular part of the process
can't occur.
You can't have the platelets
binding to each other
and so you're not going to be able
to aggregate the platelet
and so that platelet plug
is not going to form very well.
Now another way by which
you can have a qualitative,
quality problem with the platelets
is if a patient is taking aspirin.
Remember that aspirin
irreversibly inactivates
cyclooxygenase.
That's a high yield farm principle.
That when you take aspirin
that inactivates cyclooxygenase
and it's irreversible,
that inactivation.
What's going to happen is
remember again
that when the platelets are
you know,
you've got von Willebrand's factor here
and then the platelet binds
via GP1B
and then that is going to be called
adhesion
and then the next step
is that you're going to get
once this adhesion occurs
degranulation and release of mediators
and one of the mediators
was ADP
which we've already talked about
and another mediator
was TXA2
or thromboxyne2.
I told you
several times now
that thromboxyne2
is actually derived
from platelet cyclooxygenase
and this is an essential component
of this reaction
because it's thromboxyne2
that sort of calls in
the other platelets
and says,
hey guys,
let's aggregate.
Alright,
let's join together.
And so if you don't have
platelet cyclooxygenase
you're not going to be able
to produce this aggregation step.
And so that would result in
a qualitative disorder
of the platelets.
So the quality of the platelets
would be bad.
And so platelet aggregation
would not be able
to occur properly.
The last of the qualitative disorders
that we're going to discuss
is uremia.
Uremia,
you recall,
is a state that a patient enters
when they have
poor kidney function.
And that results in a buildup
of nitrogenous waste products.
So that's called uremia.
And this uremia
will disrupt platelet function
by creating disorders
of both adhesion
and aggregation
so that the platelets
don't generally tend
to function well
when patients are uremic.
And that is the end
of our discussion
of primary hemostasis.
In the next section
we're going to go into
secondary hemostasis.
Thank you.
All right.